Finding Aid for Anatomical Donations Program (University of Michigan) records, 1881-1990.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Anatomical Donations Program (University of Michigan) Records 1881-1980
University of Michigan. Anatomical Donations Program.
3.5 linear ft.
950 Bimu 2
Unit of the University of Michigan concerned with the procurement of cadavers for anatomical instruction, includes registers and permits detailing the acquisition and tracking of cadavers for medical instruction at the University of Michigan
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Accession No. 2937 ) was received through the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology in 1994.
The collection is open for research.
Although the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology has legally been receiving bodies since the latter part of the nineteenth century, the present Anatomical Donations Program was established in 1958, under Act 138 of the Public Acts of 1958 and modified as the Uniform Anatomical Gift Act (Act 189 of the Public Acts of 1969).
When the University of Michigan Medical School began instruction in 1850, the need for cadavers for practical study soon developed. By 1852 practical anatomy was a requirement and dissection work one of the required laboratory courses. During these early years it was incumbent upon the demonstrator of anatomy to supply the necessary cadavers. Lacking any public law governing the procurement of bodies, the early history of the department of anatomy is rife with stories of grave-robbing and body-snatching. As the available supply of bodies was exhausted, the demonstrator was forced to rely on outside agents to supply the needs of the Medical School. These agents or "resurrectionists," often supplied the school with some rather infamous cadavers.
In 1867, the state of Michigan passed the first anatomical act, "authorizing the dissection in certain cases for the advancement of science," and provided that unclaimed bodies from state hospitals and prisons be provided to medical schools. This act failed to provide any means of enforcement and was modified in 1875 to include penalties for non-compliance.
Despite the passage of legislation there remained a shortage of bodies for study. In a report to the Board of Regents on July 28, 1880, anatomical demonstrator William Herdman addressed the on-going issue of grave-robbing. In his report he specified the three levels of recourse for procuring bodies. The first goal was to "exhaust all strictly legal sources of supply," followed by an effort "to complete the supply from the surplus at other colleges," and finally to "draw from the pauper and friendless dead at our county houses and asylums."
(University of Michigan Medical School, "Report on Grave Robbing," by William Herdman, 1880, Box 135).
The 1875 act continued to be modified throughout the nineteenth century and into the early twentieth century. It was not until 1958 that an entirely new anatomical act was passed. Authored primarily by Russell T. Woodburne, chairman of the University of Michigan Department of Anatomy, the new act established an anatomical committee and created rules for the transportation, preservation and allocation of anatomical material.
Since 1958, the handling of anatomical material has been controlled by the State Anatomical Board in accordance with Michigan law. The State Board consists of one appointed member from each of the four state institutions legally authorized to receive anatomical material and one ex-officio member from the Michigan Department of Public Health.
Currently the University of Michigan maintains an active file of over 18,000 enrollment forms from prospective donors. Upon approval, cadavers accepted by the Medical School are given registry numbers and the majority of them are embalmed for future use in gross anatomy courses. Following study, which may be up to 18 months after donation, individual cadavers are cremated and their ashes collected and stored in catalogued containers. Families of donors have the option of having the ashes returned or may have them interred during the annual memorial service conducted by the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology.
Over the years the location of the memorial services has changed. Information on interments prior to 1942 appears to be nonexistent. Information on the location and approximate time periods of interments is given below:
1942-1963 Fairview Cemetery (1401 Wright St.)
1963-1987 United Memorial Gardens (4800 Curtis Road, Plymouth)
1988- Washtenong Memorial Park (3771 Whitmore Lake Road)
For further information on the Department of Anatomy and the procurement of anatomical material the researcher is advised to consult the following:
Huelke, Donald F., "History of the Department of Anatomy The University of Michigan: Part I. 1850-1894." The University of Michigan Medical Bulletin, Vol. 27, no. 1, Jan.-Feb. 1961
For two detailed accounts of grave-robbing cases that involved the University of Michigan the researcher should consult the following:
Holtz, William, "Jesse James and the Medical School: Bankrobbers, Burkers, and Bodysnatchers." Michigan Quarterly Review, Vol. VI, no. 2, April 1967 (pp. 90-98)
Sievers, Harry J.,"The Harrison Horror," Public Library of Fort Wayne and Allen County, 1955.
These records document the acquisition and tracking of cadavers for medical instruction at the University of Michigan for nearly a century, beginning in 1881. Although these records were created to fulfill an administrative need, researchers will find that the records contain an abundance of information. In addition to the obvious genealogical information, quantitative and qualitative statistics on causes of death and ages of death can be extracted from these records. This documentation also provides commentary on changing social values, as the sources of cadavers moved from unclaimed paupers, to the development of program sustained by voluntary donations.
The records are divided into the following series:
Anatomical Materials Register, 1881-1974 (2 linear ft.)
Burial-Transit Permits, 1943-1980 (1.5 linear ft.)
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy; Human anatomy; Human dissection; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan
- Anatomical Materials Register, 1881-1974, 2 linear ft.
  Each incoming cadaver was assigned a sequential registry number by the Medical School. These numbers are recorded in a series of ledgers beginning with number 1 on March 7, 1881 and ending with number 20,000 which was received on July 22, 1974. This first series, Anatomical Materials Register, consists of nine bound ledgers and four loose leaf post binders that cover the period from 1881 to 1974. Although the information contained in the ledgers varies over time, these records typically include name, age, date of death, cause of death, and method of shipment. Occasionally the names of physicians and relatives are supplied as is information on the disposition of the body. The entries are generally chronological although delays in shipping the cadaver may translate into a juxtaposition of the chronology.
  - Ledgers
    - Volume I (1-1,858), March 7, 1881 - September 20, 1897 (Box 1)
    - Volume II (1,860-3,800), October 10, 1897 - July 18, 1916 (Box 1)
    - Volume III (3,801-5,800), July 21, 1916 - February 10, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Volume IV (5,801-7,790), February 10, 1925 - February 2, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Volume V (7,791-9,780), February 3, 1931 - January 8, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Volume VI (9,781-11,790), January 12, 1937 - March 6, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Volume VII (11,791-13,780), March 6, 1941 - May 12, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Volume VIII (13,781-15,769), May 13, 1947 - May 4, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Volume IX (15,770-16,521), May 4, 1955 - July 23, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Loose Leaf Binders
    - Volume X (16,515-17,489), July 24, 1958 - June 24, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Volume XI (17,490-18,347), June 29, 1962 - August 8, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Volume XII (18,348-19,249), August 12, 1966 - May 17, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Volume XIII (19,250-20,000), May 7, 1971 - July 22, 1974 (Box 2)
- Burial-Transit Permits, 1943-1980, 1.5 linear ft.
  The Burial-Transit Permits, issued by the Michigan Department of Health, represent documentation that was required to accompany the remains during transportation. The permits begin in January 1943 and end in 1975, with the exception of a separate sequence of baby burial-transit permits that date from 1965 to 1980 (earlier baby burial-transit permits are interfiled with the regular permits). These permits contain information that generally parallels that which is provided in the anatomical materials register. The registry number appears on each of the permits and can be cross referenced to the registry. From 1943 to 1964 the permits are sequentially arranged. Beginning in 1965 the permits are arranged alphabetically by name within each year.
  - Permits 12,436-16,390, January 1943 - December 1957 (Box 3)
  - Permits 16,391-20,240, January 1958 - August 1975 (Box 4)
  - Baby Permits (ca. 18,000-21,600), 1965-1980, (For earlier years baby permits are interfiled with the general permits.) (Box 5)